Like many others, I was quite surprised
to see that Trump and his cronies are
actually going ahead with their little
trade war. Some have postulated that
tariffs are just a bluff, part of some
backwards 4D chess negotiation tactic.
And yet, here we are, 100 plus% tariffs
between China and the US. In principle,
the Trump team's plan is quite simple.
By imposing tariffs, they want to a
isolate China while providing leverage
for negotiations with other countries
and b turn the US back into an
industrial exportoriented economy. But
could any of these plans ever work even
to a limited extent? Let's take a look.
First, let's consider point A. Isolating
China and gaining leverage in trade
negotiations with other countries. Just
what does the Trump team plan to do here
exactly? Especially with the whole
threatening your closest allies bit.
Have they gone mental or is there a plan
behind all this? Some might ask. Well,
there is a plan in fact, and it's quite
mental. Yanis Farufakis wrote about this
recently in an article you should
definitely check out after this video.
The plan here seems to be to basically
split the world into two camps. Those
who get to enjoy economic closeness to
and military protection by America and
those who do not. So the first category
would include most Western nations and
most other West aligned countries. The
second category would then include the
likes of China and Russia. So what's the
catch? Well, countries of the first
category get to benefit from lower
tariffs and military protection at the
low low price of America dominating
their economies. Basically, they would
be forced to let in American exports
move their industrial bases to the US
and then function as export markets for
American products as America makes bank
on this arrangement. Those countries
that remain outside of this protection
record will be forced to pay the US in
the form of tariffs. So, is this plan
viable? To quote an eternal
classic, doesn't work. Never going to
happen. Turns out other countries might
have differing opinions on this issue.
If you try to strongarm a bunch of
countries into becoming your economic
vessel states, they might just have
something to say about it. Especially
when it comes to economic books, which
are about the same size as the US, like
the European Union. See, these
prospective vessel states might just
start talking among each other, saying
things like, "Wow, it would sure suck to
lose our industry and become
economically subservient to a country
run by a bunch of incompetent weird
idiots." The EU is even giving it staff
burner phones to stop them from being
spied on in the US. And isn't that
something? Burner phones are useful, but
regular people need something more
practical. Well, now, thanks to NordVPN,
you can keep malicious actors out of
your private life. Available both on
Android, iOS, and PC, NordVPN protects
your privacy and personal data with just
a single click. It even alerts you if
you visit a fake online store and if
you're about to fall victim to a scam,
thanks to NordVPN's threat protection
pro feature, which also doubles as a
certified anti-ishing tool, protecting
you from fishing websites. and as a
brand new feature, the dark web monitor,
alerting you in case your credentials
are leaked anywhere, so you can take
steps immediately. The only thing it
cannot protect you from is inviting a
journalist to your illegal signal chat
room, where you discuss US attack plans.
NordVPN also protects you from malware
by blocking dangerous ads and not
letting you stray into malware infested
websites. All this is integrated into
the NordVPN app itself, so no need to
download additional bloatware. NordVPN
is also a useful tool if you travel a
lot, especially on public transit. I
like to use their service when using
public Wi-Fi networks on longer train
trips. Additionally, if access is
limited by time or amount of data, you
can just flip a switch and use those
limits all over again. Get NordVPN's
2-year plan plus 4 months free using my
link
nordvpn.com/adamthing, which you will
also find in the description.
Subscribing is risk-free since it comes
with a 30-day money back guarantee.
Thanks to NordVPN for sponsoring today's
video. So prospective vessel states see
that the US is run by a bunch of idiots.
So they instead form their own economic
alliance leaving the US out of it like
the EU measur trade agreement or the EU
India free trade agreement or a
potential EU China trade agreement. And
this aggressive American posturing also
incentivizes countries to look for a new
global reserve currency, one that isn't
controlled by a bunch of weird idiots
like the euro. And the letter is a
particularly big problem for Trump and
company. Global US financial dominance.
Their ultimate leverage hinges on a
strong US dollar, which is the result of
it being the global reserve currency. If
that status is gone, then suddenly the
US becomes just another country. The
reason why other countries put up with
Trump's [__] is because America is
the global financial center of the
world. They cannot be circumvented
because they control the global reserve
currency. But now it seems the Trump
admin no longer wants to have that role,
which is insane. Their reasons for not
wanting it actually ties into their
second goal, turning the US back into an
industrial export- oriented economy. In
the second half of the 20th century,
America was famous for its
manufacturing. This was the era when
places like Detroit were at their
height. Those idealized times when a
factory worker was considered middle
class and when the whole family could
live on a single manufacturing salary.
That world is gone, and the formerly
booming towns and cities have since
become rapidly depopulating urban
wastelands, ravaged by poverty, opioids,
and neglect. And so Trump and company
want to turn back the clock by forcing
companies to return their manufacturing
to the US, reviving the great industrial
heartland, ushering in a new golden age
of economic growth. That's the plan
anyway. And the reasonable question to
ask here is [__] how? The US economy
is quite simply not set up for major
industrialization and exports. It's set
to siphon money out of everything it can
to make shareholders richer. These are
what we call stock buybacks. Basically,
when a company makes $100 million, the
company does not spend it on
development. Instead, it gives the money
to shareholders. And for shareholders,
this is great. But for the companies and
their employees, not so much. What if
there is a bad year right after the
stock buyback? Well, let's use our
financial reserves to get through it.
But hold on, we gave it all to
shareholders last year. Uh-oh, looks
like it's time for mass layoffs. So, the
end result is mass poverty and
joblessness for workers as shareholders
pocket millions of dollars. This is a
systemic issue that needs to be
addressed with regulation, something the
Trump team is notably not willing to do
because that would go against the
interest of the oligarchs backing them.
Additionally, bringing major industrial
capacities to the US is not a trivial
task. It's not like those logistics
centers you see popping up next to
cities where they just build a big metal
box and a month later it's already fully
up and running. Heavy industry is a bit
different from that if you can imagine.
You need industrial scale utilities
built out. Roads, railroads, water,
hazardous waste disposal, industrial
water treatment. You need to upgrade the
electricity grid. It's not a trivial
task. And considering how the US
manufacturing base has been left to rot
for the past five decades, all of it
needs to be rebuilt from scratch. And
that would take years and billions and
billions of dollars. And much of the
industrial equipment needed to start
those factories is made in what country?
Yeah, China. A country currently subject
to 100 plus% tariffs. And these tariffs
would need to stay in place indefinitely
for US manufacturing to survive. The
second the tariffs are gone, companies
would start moving back to China due to
lower production costs. Also,
unemployment in the US is very low.
Staffing those factories would require a
large workforce. You usually get that
through immigration, except the Trump
team is gearing up for mass deportation,
which is notably the opposite. So, this
big re-industrialization is just not
going to happen, at least not on a large
scale. Also because what if and now try
to stay with me on this. What if other
economic blocks will do to the US what
the US is doing to them right now? So
you know, hey America, that's a nice
industrial base you got there. So nice
that we have imposed 100% tariff on all
its products. Good luck. [__] you. And
the standard mega response to this is,
oh then our industry will just produce
to our own domestic market. But that
just isn't big enough to sustain an
industry the size of that of the 1970s.
If you go the industrial route, you need
to export. Period. But even if this
mythical revived US industry starts
producing to a global market tomorrow,
they would get crushed by the
competition. In 1970, exporting American
cars was easy. Not many countries were
making cars and not in such quantity or
quality. Today, we have a Chinese EV
sector far outpacing any Western
producer. Competitors are cheaper, more
efficient, and more technologically
advanced. You know, in Europe, sometimes
you see American pickup trucks. They are
mostly driven by socially maladapted
middle-aged men unwilling to peacefully
coexist in human society. Such pickup
trucks are thankfully a very rare sight
because they are horribly expensive,
needlessly large, and consume more than
three times the fuel compared to an
average European car. Basically, you
need to commit very hard to the [__]
bit to actually get one. And the reason
for American pickup's monstrous size is
to flee customers, nothing more. US car
companies were looking for ways to sell
more cars and figured that instead of
selling more cars to more customers,
they could just sell each customer more
car singular. Why sell you a one-tonon
hatchback when they can also sell you a
2.5 ton pickup? With the pickup, you're
essentially paying for two and a half
cars while getting only one. And while
this practice is great for the American
market, turns out the global market is
rather limited when it comes to $80,000
oversized gas guzzlers. Imagine that
many American products are just not
viable as exports. They are designed to
fleece US customers in a protected
market, not to compete abroad. And it's
not like the US lets competitors cars
into its domestic market like Chinese
EVs to compete with American cars. So
why would other countries let in
American cars? So if America wants to
become an export powerhouse, it must
ensure that there are as few tariffs as
possible as low as possible. But wasn't
this the exact problem so far that Trump
and company have been raging about?
Their problem is with the current global
system of free trade, which supposedly
disadvantages US industry. But that's
mostly due to the way the US economy
works, which I've talked about earlier,
focusing on paying out investors instead
of actual development. It's not that the
US has been getting bad deals from other
countries. It's that US industrial
products are not that great anymore, and
that the US financial sector has turned
the industrial sector and the whole
country for that matter into their very
own ATM machine. This is a result of the
global neoliberal economic system and a
lack of US financial sector regulations.
Now, this system has worked out quite
well for quite a few people. This is
where the elephant curve comes in,
showing us that in this system, pretty
much everyone profited except for the
world's poorest and the western middle
class. Additionally, the top 1% profited
a lot. A 60% income growth is very
different when you're making $15 a day
versus 15 million. Okay, so with all
that in mind, let's recap. The US tries
to strongarm allies into becoming
economic vessels, wants to bring back
manufacturing to its territory, and
seeks to become an exportoriented
economy. But the allies or former allies
are fighting back and will not become
vessels. The US would need more workers,
but it's currently getting ready for
mass deportations. US products are not
cutting edge at best and or a scheme to
fleece customers at worst. And the US
economy is set to extract money from
industry, not vice versa. And on top of
this comes yet another problem, US
military power. The upkeep of which is
completely incompatible with the US
being an export economy. And just how
does that work? Currency. Every country
has it. If your currency is strong, you
can buy more stuff from other countries
whose currencies are weaker. If your
currency is weak, you can sell more
stuff to other countries whose
currencies are stronger. For example,
let's say the US dollar and the euro are
perfectly equal. $1 equals€1 and that
the EU US tariffs are zero. So, if a
European car company makes a car costing
€20,000, a US customer can buy it for
$20,000. But if the dollar is stronger,
so let's say $1 equals €2, then that
€20,000 car would only cost $10,000 for
the US customer. A strong currency is
great when you want to buy stuff from
abroad because you can get it for cheap.
On the other hand, if the dollar is
weaker, so let's say $2 equal€1, then
that €20,000 European-made car will cost
$40,000 for the US customer. On the flip
side, now the Americanmade car costing
$20,000 will only cost €10,000 to the
European customer. So now the US can go
nuts with its exports, revving up those
factories, ushering in a new golden age
of manufacturing. Except US military
power kind of hinges on a strong dollar.
With the fact that it's the global
reserve currency, the US dollar is
highly valued no matter what. Enabling
the US to upkeep a military of such size
and strength. Building and maintaining
their military depends on many, many
foreign suppliers. To give you just one
example, major parts of the F-35 are
made in the UK, Japan, Norway, Denmark,
Canada, Netherlands, Italy, Austria, and
so on. And all those parts are made
cheaper for the US by a strong US
dollar. And you also can't just move
these hyper complex supply chains to the
US overnight. It would take decades,
assuming that all those other countries
would willingly part with their military
industry and pool of experts, which they
won't. So, if you want to export stuff,
you have to weaken the dollar. But if
you weaken the dollar, the US military
needs to be downsized. But if you
downsize the US military, you undercut
the benefit of a military umbrella in
exchange for being a US vessel state.
And a weak dollar would also mean that
the rest of the world would need to look
for another global reserve currency.
Meaning the US would no longer reign
supreme in the global finance sector. So
if the US wants to become a
manufacturing powerhouse, it needs to
weaken the dollar. But then being the
world financial and military hegeimon
goes right out the [__] window, which
kills most of America's leverage on the
global stage. As in, why would China,
India, or the EU listen to Trump at that
point? The EU is the world's new
financial center, and the Chinese,
Indian, and European armies are now on
par with the American. So why should
they give a [__] about what Trump wants
or thinks? Give us what we want, world,
or we'll stop exporting our overpriced,
oversized, shitty pickup trucks. Oh no,
what a disaster. Right when those rural
Chinese and Indian families were
clamoring to buy a Ford F-150 Raptor
with the supercharged Predator V8
engine, no. Come on. No. Trump's plan
will not work. They're trying to have
their cake and eat it too, basically.
So, with that being said, what would
work? Regulations and investing into
American society's welfare. Limiting the
amount of stock buybacks so companies
will invest into themselves instead of
functioning as ATM machines for finance.
Bros, linking decaying areas with
high-speed rail to plug them back into
the economic circulation. Spreading
major corporations sites across the
country so they aren't all concentrated
in like three cities, making those
places completely unaffordable.
eliminating legal loopholes car makers
use to bypass environmental regulations
to sell giant pickup trucks instead of
regular cheaper economical cars.
Enacting Medicare for all so that people
no longer die on the streets due to
curable diseases because they couldn't
afford treatment in the richest country
on the planet. Nationalize universities
so they start functioning as actual
places of learning instead of sports and
real estate management firms with
classrooms attached. Set a higher
federal minimum wage, more paid vacation
days, mandatory set periods. Hell, even
the 4-day work week to increase
employees well-being. Overhaul zoning
laws so that more housing can be built
in areas that need it the most, driving
down the cost of living. These are just
some of the things the US government
could do to help restore its middle
class and lift millions out of poverty.
The problem is not that manufacturing is
gone. It's that the economy is set up to
suck everyone and everything dry. There
is still an ungodly amount of money
circulating in the US economy. It's just
that ordinary people see less and less
of it since more and more of that money
is concentrated at the top. It's that
simple. America's economy is like a
rickety rust the old gasg guzzler wreck
of a car driven by a bunch of finance
bros desperate to ring as much profit
out of it as possible before it breaks
apart completely. The car has been
getting slower for the past decades and
the rattling noises are getting louder.
The car needs a complete overhaul. But
instead of that, Trump just wants to
slap a V12 engine into it and call it a
day. The US needs systemic changes. Not
today, not yesterday, more like 20 years
ago. An overcharged manufacturing
sector, if feasible at all, might be
able to mask problems for a while, but
eventually they will all come back to
haunt America. If by then there will be
an America at all, which at this rate
I'm not so sure of, honestly.
[Music]